um you know how do we learn from the old
and confront the new well I think the I
think we can draw many very good lessons
from the early period of the Industrial
Revolution of course earlier in England
but let's take care of the United States
the Industrial Revolution took off right
around here eastern Massachusetts mid
nineteenth century this was a period
when independent farmers were being
driven into the industrial system men
and women incidentally women from the
farms of gold factory girls and they
bitterly resented it they had it was a
period with very Free Press the most in
the in the history of the country there
was a wide variety of journals and the
ethnic labor others and when you read
them they're pretty fascinating the
people driven into the industrial system
regarded it is an attack on their
personal dignity on their rights as
human beings they were free human beings
who were being forced into what they
called wage slavery which they regarded
is not very different from chattel
slavery in fact this was such a popular
view that it was actually a slogan of
the Republican Party that the only
difference between working for a wage
and being a slave is that working for a
wage or supposedly temporary the
prisoner will be free other than that
they're not different and they bitterly
resented the fact that the the
industrial system was even taking away
their rich cultural life and the
cultural life was rich another by now
studies of the British working-class and
American working class and they were
part of high culture of the day Ike I
remember this is later the 1930s with my
own family industrial you know so
unemployed working-class and they said
this was being taken away from us we're
being forced to be something like slaves
they argued that if you if you're say a
journeyman craftsman and you sell your
product you're selling what you produced
if your wage if your wage earner you're
selling yourself which is deeply
offensive they condemned what they
called the new spirit of the age gained
wealth for getting old but self sounds
familiar and it was extremely radical it
was combined with a the most radical
Democratic movement in American history
the populist the early populist movement
the radical farmers began in Texas
spreaded to the Midwest enormous
movement of farmers who wanted to free
themselves from the domination by the
northeastern bankers and capitalists
cousin ran the markets you know sort of
forced them to a silver what they
produced on credit and squeezed them
with credit and so on they went on to
develop their own banks to run
cooperatives they started to link up
with the Knights of Labor major labor
movement which held that as they put it
those those who work in the mills or
owned them that should be a Democrat
free democratic society these were very
powerful movements by the 1890s
you know workers were taking over towns
and running them in eastern Pennsylvania
and western Pennsylvania homesteads and
famous keys well they were crushed by
force